טוב *Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is דף כ"ח *Daf Kaf-Ches*, dedicated to
the learning in memory of Joe's wife גאלדי *Goldie*, whose her third
יארצייט *yahrtzeit* today, right? It's גאלדי בת גאלדא בת יצחק יהודה *Goldie
bas Golda bas Yitzchak Yehuda*. Should be in her memory and in
her זכות *zechus*.
So we pick up with the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, interesting in terms
of that, in terms of the context of this משנה Mishnah *mishna*
on כ"ח עמוד amud א' *Kaf-Ches amud-aleph*, let's take a look. המביא
גט get *Hamavei get*, somebody is delivering a גט get, *get*. So
you maybe this is we're starting to get an idea why the
whole first מסכת *masechet* opens with an idea of שליחות *shelichus* because
it allows for the exploring of some interesting scenarios, right? So we
dealt with what happens if the גט get *get* gets lost by
the שליח *shaliach*, and now we deal with the following case. המביא
גט והניחו זקן hamevi get v'henicho zaken, *Hamavei get vehiniho zaken*, so
you left the husband, he was old. או חולה *O holeh*, or
he was sick. נותנין לה בחזקת שהוא חי *Nosin lo bechezkas shehu
chayam*. The גט get *get* can be delivered on the presumption that
he is still alive and she'll be believers, and then she'll treat
herself as divorced and, you know, with the relevant consequences. Presumably, she
won't have to worry about יבום yibum *yibum*, she won't have to
wait for word that he's dead and so on. Although no, actually,
if she had pre- if he had died before it, then either
way she would know that she could be married. So the point
is right, obviously she could be married one way or the other,
the basic- the basic issue is יבום yibbum *yibum*. Now you have
to understand that this also means that even if she finds out
later that he died, it's quite possible that there's going to be
no way to precisely date the, you know, the things, and it'll
never be determined. So it's not necessarily on the presumption because like
well you could always figure it out later, you might never get
that information, you know, and you just work with that assumption that
he's still alive and that's how you go forward. חזקה chazakah *Chazaka*,
he was alive then, you assume he's alive now. בת ישראל bas
Yisrael הנסואה לכהן *Bas Yisrael hanesua leKohen*, now let's say you have
a woman who's a ישראלי *Yisraeli*, daughter of a ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*
man, and she's married to a כהן Kohen. *Kohen* and as- by
virtue of being married to a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* she eats תרומה
terumah, *Terumah*. והלך בעלה למדינת הים l'medinas hayam, *Vehalach baalah limdinas hayam*,
and her husband goes overseas. אוכלת בתרומה בחזקת שהוא חי *Ocheles baterumah
bechezkas shehu chayam*, she eats תרומה Terumah *Terumah* on the presumption that
he's alive, right, forever? And that- now of course the question is
I mean how long? For a hundred years? I mean okay, but-
but anyway for many many years she can continue to eat תרומה
Terumah? *Terumah*. And she doesn't have to be afraid that he might
have died. השולח חטאתו ממדינת הים hasholeiach chataso mimedinas hayam, *Hasholeiach chataso
mimdinas hayam*,
somebody who sends a חטאת chatas *chatas* from מדינת הים medinat hayam,
*medinas hayam*, from overseas, so מקריבים אותה בחזקת שהוא חי *makrivim osa
bechezkas shehu chayam*.
Then you bring it on the presumption that he's alive. If he
weren't alive it would be a חטאת שמתו בעליה *chatas shemeisu baaleha*,
it would have to go למיתה *limisa*, couldn't be brought as a
קרבן korban. *korban*. And nevertheless, you can presume that he's still alive.
The biggest חידוש chiddush *chidush* I would say of all of these,
I mean you could sort of say well גיטין Gittin *gittin* is
very weighty, it's אשת איש *eishes ish*, although again either way she's
either גרושה *gerusha* או אלמנה *o almanah*, you know, תרומה Terumah, *Terumah*
for זר *zari*, תרומה Terumah. *Terumah* is חייב מיתה בידי שמים *chayav
misa bidei shamayim*, you know, so maybe that's why תרומה Terumah. *Terumah*
is the biggest חידוש *chidush*. But in my mind תרומה Terumah. *Terumah*
is the biggest חידוש *chidush* because it's ongoing. All these other cases,
it's like you just have to say at this one moment he's
still alive and presumably that one moment wasn't so long after, you
know, even if it took a year to get from מדינת הים
medinat hayam *medinas hayam*, it wasn't so long, right? Whereas the תרומה
Terumah *Terumah*, you're not allowing one thing and making a presumption of
one moment, you're making an ongoing presumption, you know, indefinitely.
And so yeah. Say he was 90 years old, she was 20.
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going to deal with
a little bit to some degree. So let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Nothing to do with quality of communication, right?
In other words, right, yeah, correct. You mean what you're saying is
let's say it's easy to make the phone call. Okay, so that's
a good point, meaning, you know, when we rely on a חזקה
chazakah, *chazaka*, you know, when we use any of these types of
ברור *berur* to determine certain things, do we say that if אפשר
לברר *efshar levarer* you have to be מברר meva'rer. *mevarer*? And how,
right? You know, right, so if it's אפשר לברר *efshar levarer* easily.
So that's a good point. Normally we do say that. However, I
would say, I would say that when we do say that,
there has to be what's called like a לידת הספק *leidas hasefek*.
So, you know, for example, we when we שחוט *shecht* an animal
we don't שחוט *shecht* for all of the organs to make sure
that they're not טרף *treif*, that would be enormously time and cost,
you know, a big, a big expense in terms of time and
cost, and the price of meat would probably double. So what we
do is we say, well you only have to check the lungs
because there's only, there's only like, everything else we call a מיעוט
דמיעוטא *miut de-miuta*, like a trivial possibility that it could be a
problem, whereas the lungs it's more, it's more common that it's a
problem, so that you have to be מברר meva'rer *mevarer*. So there's
not, everything else you just rely on רוב *rov* or you rely
on, you know, that it's not a problem. So the point is
that you don't have to be מברר *mevarer* even if you're able
to be מברר *mevarer* if it's considered to be a מיעוט לא
lo, שכיח *miut lo shchiach*, like a trivial minority of cases. Now
what is that, what is that percentage? Some say it's under 5%
or under 10%. Okay. but if it's a trivial, if it's a
מיעוט שלא שכיח trivial possibility, you don't have to check for it.
Now it's an interesting question here because here you might want to
say there's a different reason you don't have to check and
it's the לידא דספק. leida d'safek. You know what I mean? It's
like, it's like in the case of at, I mean, in the
case of a, of a שחיטה shechting the animal for example, you
know that there are all, all there's a certain percentage of animals
that have problems in their inner organs. Here, maybe the point of
the חזקה chazakah is, once you know, you assume the current status
obtains. You knew he was definitely alive, right? You never knew what
the status of the organs of the animals were, but you know
he was definitely alive, so who's raising a question? If someone says,
wait wait wait, I heard something or maybe or whatever, but until
there's a ספק, safek, a לידא דספק, leida d'safek, right, maybe you
don't have to worry about it, so don't have to be מברר.
So that's an interesting question, right? So at what stage would you
have to be מברר if it was trivially easy? All right, let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara What does the גמרא Gemara
say that? Let's say you actually heard something, then do you have
to? Well, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara because the
גמרא Gemara will at least deal with some cases. It is also
worth noting that all the cases in the משנה Mishnah explicitly mention
מדינת הים, medinat hayam? right? Oh, actually not the first one. The
first one is implicit, but then it's הלך בעלה למדינת הים, halach
ba'alah l'medinat hayam, שלח גט ממדינת הים, shalach get mimedinat hayam, gets
us back to that sense of that gap and that distance, you
know, that that first משנה Mishna opened up between מדינת הים medinat
hayam. and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and that inability to actually access
what's going on, right? So it is sort of echoing that. Okay,
let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא שנו אלא זקן,
lo shanu ela zaken, only if he's just סתם stam old, אבל
שלא הגיע לגבורות, aval shelo higia ligvurot, but he's not yet eighty
years old, ואם בגבורות שמונים שנה. v'im bigvurot shmonim shanah. Okay, וחולה
v'choleh or a sick person, שרוב חולים לחיים, sherov cholim lachayim, because
most sick people get better, you're just סתם stam sick, okay. אבל
זקן שהגיע לגבורות, aval zaken shehigia ligvurot, but if he's elderly and
he's already eighty years old, וגוסס v'goses or he's a גוסס, goses,
which is an interesting question of how to define, sometimes the גוסס
goses is defined as like actively in the process of dying, okay,
but certainly somebody that's there like, you know, terminal and and on
his way to dying, שרוב גוססים למיתה, sherov gosesim l'mitah, thank you
so much, that the majority of גוססים gosesim do die, לא, then
those people you could not assume that they are still alive. That
maybe for him would be considered something like a לידא דספק leida
d'safek or
a חזקה עשויה להשתנות. chazakah asuyah l'hishtanot. Yet that is their current
status, but there's already evidence that that's a, that it's in the
process of changing. So he said is that only because of מדינת
הים? Medinas HaYam But let's say it was a town over, you
wouldn't have to do that? Even if he's on his deathbed? Why?
Why why would it be different? Just because it was only a
day ago? Well, you think these cases are, was mostly, you know?
Yeah, but I don't know, no, the חידוש of the משנה Mishna
is even מדינת הים. medinas hayam? But if once he's saying that
you can't rely on a חזקה, Chazaka. presumably you couldn't rely even
a day later, you know? So how do you ever do this?
I don't know, I mean, or maybe you get the information afterwards,
you do it and you mark the date and then you find
out, you know, and so on. I don't know, you're right, like,
you know, well the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about that, like
what? I mean תוספות Tosafot says what, you mean when you step
out of the house? Like let's say we would say that a
זקן שהגיע לגבורות, zaken shehigia ligvurot, so the woman when she goes
to the store, she goes to her friend, she can't eat תרומה,
Terumah. right? So exactly, so תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, might have, there
obviously might be some factor of time built in here. We'll get
to that תוספות, Tosafot, that's a good point. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, איתיביה אביי, Eitiveih Abaye, אביי Abaye challenges, המביא
גט get והניחו זקן, we have a ברייתא, braita, אפילו בן מאה
שנה, afilu ben me'ah shanah, even if he's a hundred years old,
נותנו לו בחזקת שהוא קיים, notno lo bechezkas shehu kayam, so you
see we have the חזקה Chazaka even if the guy's very old,
okay. תיובתא, Tiuvta,
that's a challenge. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima,
if you want, I can try to support still רבא's Rava statement
and say, כיון דאיפרק איפרק, keivan de'ifrak ifrak, once he made it
that far, this guy has real longevity genes. Okay, normal people after
eighty, you've got to be afraid they'll die sometime soon, but once
a guy gets that old, till how old? 100? So רש״י Rashi
says 90. I don't know how רש״י Rashi knew 90, but yeah,
once you reach the age of 95, you're no more likely to
die any single day than you were when you reached that, you
plateau. Uh huh. And there's not an increasing chance? No. But until
then it's an increasing chance? Interesting. Okay, interesting. Anyway, so that's, anyway,
that's the answer. Now the other thing is that it's one thing
old, because there's nothing, like there's no different halachic status of being
old, right? I mean אביי Abaye tries to create, רבא Rava tries
to create that status by calling it גבורות, gvurot, but that's not
a halachic status. גוסס Goses is very different. גוסס Goses is somebody
that there really is a different halachic status, like there's a הלכה
halacha that if somebody is a גוסס, goses, you're not allowed to
touch him because you're afraid that the very act of touching him
will cause him to die. Okay, so there really is a halachic
status of גוסס. goses. So to say that a גוסס goses doesn't
have a חזקת חיים chezkat chayim is different than saying an old
person doesn't. So even when the גמרא's Gemara challenging רבא's Rava statement
about an old person, you know, the statement about a גוסס goses
presumably makes a lot of sense.
And הגיע higia here means he
reached it? Yeah. He sailed into that? Exactly, exactly, exactly. Okay, or
he
distinguished Alright, so anyway, so we don't know if to limit the
משנה Mishna to a case where he's not yet super old or
80 or whatever, to limit the case of a משנה Mishna to
somebody who's not in a serious illness. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. תנן, Tnan, okay.
רמי ליה אביי לרבא. Rami la Abaye le-Rabba. אביי Abaye challenged רבא
Rava with the two, this contradiction. תנן, Tnan, our משנה Mishna says:
המביא גט והניחו זקן או חולה נותנו לה בחזקת שהוא קיים. Hamavee
get ve-hineecho zaken o choleh notno lo be-chezkas she-hu kayam. You can
assume he's still alive. ורמינהו, U-re-mi-ni-hu, I'll challenge you on this: הרי
זה גיטך שעה אחת קודם למיתתי, Harei zeh giteych sha'ah achas kodem
le-misasi, or so somebody says, this is your גט get, that should
take a place one minute before I die.
And he's a כהן. Kohen, אסורה לאכול בתרומה מיד. Asura le-chol bi-terumah
mi-yad. The wife immediately cannot eat תרומה Terumah because he might already...
he might die the next minute. Right, he might die the next
minute. So you see we're afraid that somebody will die at any
time. Okay, so how do you reconcile? What? Even if he's healthy
or young? Even if he's healthy and young. So how does that
reconcile with our משנה Mishna that says you're not afraid a guy
will die? So אמר ליה: amar leh: תרומה אגיטין קרמית? Terumah a-gittin
ka-ramis? What, you're challenging a case of גיטין from תרומה? Terumah. תרומה
אפשר אפשר ולא אפשר. Terumah efshar efshar ve-lo efshar. תרומה, Terumah, you
can manage. Don't eat תרומה. Terumah. By גט, get this woman's got
to get on with her life. Okay, so just because we make
a presumption by גט get doesn't mean we make it by תרומה.
Terumah Of course, the next line in our משנה Mishnah. is תרומה.
Terumah So תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, we're just building up. ורמי תרומה
אתרומה. U-re-mi terumah a-terumah. Fine, so let's challenge תרומה Terumah, against תרומה.
Terumah. תנן, Tnan, our משנה Mishnah. says: בת ישראל הנישאת לכהן והלך
בעלה למדינת הים אוכלת בתרומה בחזקת שהוא קיים. Bas Yisrael ha-nisu'ah le-kohen
ve-halach ba'alah li-medinas ha-yam ocheles bi-terumah be-chezkat she-hu kayam. That the woman
can eat תרומה Terumah. when her husband isn't around, assuming that he's
still alive. ורמינהו, U-re-mi-ni-hu, I'll ask you on this: הרי זה גיטך
שעה אחת קודם למיתתי אסורה לאכול בתרומה מיד. Harei zeh giteych sha'ah
achas kodem le-misasi asura le-chol bi-terumah mi-yad. That a woman, if a
guy says a גט get, takes place a minute before he dies,
immediately she can't eat תרומה. Terumah. So what's the story? Two cases
of תרומה, Terumah. why one can we assume he's alive and the
other we can't? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב אדא בר
אבא בריה דרב יצחק שאני התם שהרי אסר עליה שעה אחת קודם
למיתתו. Amar Rav Ada bar Abba brei de-Rav Yitzchak shani hasham she-harei
asar alehah sha'ah achas kodem le-misaso. Which sounds very descriptive and doesn't
really answer, and תוספות Tosafot says it's really not an answer. Okay,
well, there it's different because there it's a minute before he dies.
Yeah, that makes a difference. Why? Now, in the end the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that that really makes all the difference,
whether the question is, is he already dead or is he going
to die? But it sounds like the גמרא Gemara didn't yet understand
the difference there in the case where, well, you understand it as
a descriptive difference but not yet as an explanatory difference. In one
case, the guy's in מדינת הים medinas hayam and the question is,
is he alive right now or dead right now? I can assume
he's alive and eat תרומה. Trumah In the other case, it's yes,
he's alive right now, I'm right in front of him, but my
question is can I eat תרומה Trumah because he's going to die
in a minute from now? He also אסר... asar... he's making a
statement, he's אסר-ing asar her, as it were, right? No, I'm not...
No. דהא אסרה עליה שעה. De-ha asra alah sha'ah. Oh, yeah, but...
okay, but that's not what he said. Okay, so... okay, hold on.
So the difference is in the fact that in that case he's
saying is the question is not is he dead right now, the
question is is he going to die in a minute. Now, that's
what's going to the גמרא's Gemara going to distinguish in a minute
from now. That's going to be the difference between שמא מת shema
mes or שמא ימות. shema yamut. Why that should matter... why that
should matter we'll see in a minute, but that doesn't seem like
the גמרא Gemara at this stage understood that difference. So רש"י Rashi
says, yeah, like it's not an answer. He doesn't really... like, he's
just describing a difference but the גמרא Gemara doesn't really have an
explanation. Okay, maybe we can try to understand what he was trying
to answer from the next line. So the גמרא Gemara says, and
then we'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says. The גמרא Gemara says
like this: מתקיף לה רב פפא מידי דאיהו מיית ברישא דילמא איהי
מייתה ברישא? Maskif lah Rav Papa mi-de-ihu meiseh barishah dilma ihi meisa
barishah?
How do you know he'll die first? Maybe she'll die first. So,
okay, what did he assume therefore the guy, the answer was that
he responded how do you know he'll die first? So it sounds
like what he's saying is that he assumed the answer was look,
in this case by the תרומה Trumah where where he said it'll
take effect a minute before I die, eventually she's going to be
אסורה asura to eat תרומה, Trumah right? Right, when he dies. So
there will be a moment in time that she'll be... that he
will be both alive and she'll be אסורה asura to eat תרומה.
Trumah, Is that clear? When he says this will be the גט
get that'll take effect a minute before I die, there will be
a moment in time in this woman's life where he will be
alive and in her presence and she'll be אסורה asura to eat
תרומה. Trumah. What moment will it be? That minute before he dies.
So therefore we're חושש choshesh that that's this minute. Okay, okay, whereas
in the other case, right, you know, there'll never be a time
when he'll be alive and she'll be אסורה asura to eat... to
eat תרומה. Trumah And the גמרא's Gemara answer is okay, but what
first of all, that's not necessarily true, there won't necessarily be a
moment that he'll be alive and she'll be אסורה. asura. Maybe she'll
die
first, right? And if she'll die first, it'll never have been a
moment in her life when he will have been alive and she'll
be אסורה asura from תרומה. Trumah? So it's already laying the groundwork
for a difference between the concern is is he already dead or
will he die, but the גמרא Gemara hasn't yet fully understood the
significance of that and it seems to be the difference as well
in one case you... know that there will be such a moment.
So therefore we have to be חושש Choshesh for it. Okay? But
the answer is no, you don't know there'll be such a moment.
Maybe she'll die first. Yes? Why is he mentioning the improbability that
she'd be actually eating תרומה Trumah, the moment he dies? And if
she's not actually eating it then he dies and she stops eating.
Yes, but any moment that she wants to eat תרומה Trumah that
might be the moment before he dies. What's the what's the probability?
Well okay, that's right, you're right, it's unlikely, you're right. So but
that but at least his answer is since there will be such
a moment, we have to always be חושש Choshesh for it. You're
right. The possibility that this is this moment is trivial. No, not
that there's this moment, but that she's actually eating תרומה Trumah at
that moment. Right, but at any moment don't eat תרומה Trumah? because
this because there will be a moment before he dies, not that
you will be eating תרומה, Trumah that it will be אסור Assur
for you to eat תרומה. Terumah. We just stop eating once he
dies. Yes, but we want her not to eat that minute. That's
what I'm saying, but what's the probability? It doesn't matter. Is it
true that assuming he's going to die first, is it true that
there'll be one minute, or let's say he says it'll take effect
an hour before I die to make it a little more whatever,
is it true that there'll be one hour while he's alive that
she's אסורה Assura to eat תרומה Terumah assuming he's going to die
first? Now is different. But let's say a minute. Is it true
that there will be a minute while he's alive that she's אסורה
Assura to eat
תרומה? Terumah But then she's not doing anything forbidden until she actually
eats. I understand, so what's the probability at that moment that she's
eating? We're going in circles. Just answer listen, I'm going to try
one more time. Let's answer the question. Is there a minute during
assuming he's going to die first, is there a minute during his
life that it will be forbidden for her to do such an
act? Yes. So at any minute that she wants to do such
an act we say don't, this might be that minute. The probability
is nil. The probability is tiny, but we're just saying since such
a minute exists, don't do it.
But this isn't like when the גמרא Gemara says you know this
is very unlikely. Right. We're not going to be concerned. Right. So
the גמרא Gemara anyway, so that's exactly it. The גמרא Gemara has
not yet come up with a good answer. Let's just keep on
going.
We're moving on. Alright, so anyway, so why is it? So the
גמרא Gemara realizes that there's a case both are cases of תרומה,
terumah but the difference is in one it's a concern is he
dead the other is concern will he die? Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara hasn't yet clarified why that matters. It seems to be the
גמרא Gemara thinks it matters because you know such a moment will
exist. Okay, but anyway that the גמרא Gemara has yet to clarify
what the why that should matter. אלא אמר אביי Ella Amar Abaye
rather says אביי Abaye לא קשיא. Lo Kashya. הא רבי מאיר דלא
חייש למיתה Ha Rabbi Meir DeLo Chayish LeMita like Michael wanted to
say הא רבי יהודה דחייש למיתה. Ha Rabbi Yehuda DeChayish LeMita. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir isn't concerned that people will die and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is even though it's ironic because normally רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir חייש למיעוטא. Chayish LeMiuta. But okay, דתנן DeTnan we taught a
משנה. Mishnah, הלוקח יין מבין הכותים HaLokeach Yayin MiBein HaKutim we saw
this before. Somebody buys wine אמר שני לוגין שאני עתיד להפריש Amar
Shnei Lugin SheAni Atid LeHafrish he's getting it from Samaritans
and it's let's say right before שבת Shabbat and he doesn't have
time to be מפריש. Mafrish. So what he says is two לוג
Log that I will separate later הרי הן תרומה Harei Hen Trumah
עשרה Asara ten of them are מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon תשעה Tisha
so there's a hundred and two, the first two are תרומה terumah.
of the hundred remaining ten are מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon of the
ninety remaining nine are מעשר שני Maaser Sheni ומיחל ושותה מיד UMeychel
UShoteh MiYad and then either begins and drinks immediately is the way
תוספות Tosafot says or רש״י Rashi says he transfers the קדושה Kedusha
of the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Anyway דברי רבי מאיר Divrei Rabbi
Meir that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. And then after שבת
Shabbat you'll designate of the wine that's left over which was the
תרומה terumah and which was the מעשר. Maaser. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי
ורבי שמעון אוסרין Rabbi Yehuda VeRabbi Yossi VeRabbi Shimon Oserin they all
forbid it. רבא אמר Rava Amar so anyway so what do you
see? If you remember how the גמרא Gemara explained that debate, it
might be a debate of יש ברירה, Yesh Brira, but the גמרא
Gemara. says no because the end of the ברייתא Baraita is is
that they say to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir aren't you afraid that
the barrel will break and there won't be any wine left over
and then they'll wind up drinking טבל Tebel because there'll be no
wine later that will have become תרומה? terumah And he says when
it breaks I'll worry about it, which means I'm not concerned it'll
break. So the גמרא Gemara understands that that's similar to a concern
of somebody dying, right, some type of maybe it's also very metaphorical,
right, you know it's like the wine, the soul contained in the
body and it breaks and the body, you know the soul runs
out. You like metaphors? But no, it's in the גמרא. Gemara
I agreed with you about that. Anyway anyway the point is is
that the גמרא Gemara understands whether because of the metaphorical similarity or
just סתם Stam like are we concerned that some accident some tragedy
will occur and change the current state of events and make a
problem so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not concerned. So maybe this
question about are you concerned that the guy will die or has
died, maybe it's a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and these
תנאים? Tannaim? Okay so that's one explanation. Yes you're right it's a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. רבא אמר Rava Amar now רבא Rava has
a more interesting answer. רבא Rava says it's not just a debate,
there really is that difference you were talking about between the two
cases. שמא מת לא חיישינן שמא ימות חיישינן Shema Met Lo Chayshinan
Shema Yamut Chayshinan whether that he's dead that's not a concern, will
he die that is a concern. Now what's the difference? Okay so
right in the case by case she eats תרומה terumah when she
leaves him when he leaves is
he
Now you could say the difference is because not everybody is dead,
but everybody will die. Okay, so, it's just true. He will die.
And maybe that's what the גמרא Gemara was getting at before, right?
Since he will die, this might be that time. But that's not
the same yet also. I mean, he will die, if he will
die, he will be dead. But it is true that everybody will
die. That doesn't go against the חזקה. Chazaka Meaning, right now it's
not true that everybody, meaning it's just whatever, it's you know, in
one case he will die, the question is just when. In the
other case it's not a question, but the basic question of will
he die? And that's the better way to frame it if you
don't like that, because that's maybe sounding too much like the previous
גמרא Gemara which the גמרא Gemara didn't like. So anyway, the sharper
way of saying it, I was just building up to the sharper
way. The sharper way of saying it is that a חזקה Chazaka
is saying we assume that the status quo still obtains. So in
one case, the status quo was that he was alive. We assume
the status quo still obtains, he's still alive, and therefore she can
eat תרומה. terumah In the other case, where the status quo was
he is alive, and we assume he's, well we don't have to
assume he's alive, he's sitting right here in front of me, right?
The point that maybe he'll die in the next hour doesn't challenge
the status quo. All the status quo tells you is that he's
alive right now. The status quo says if he was alive a
minute ago, he's alive right now. If he was alive a year
ago and you don't know anything about it, he's alive right now.
Okay? The question of can I eat תרומה terumah if it's going
to take effect an hour before he dies? That means is it,
will he die in an hour? The status quo that he is
alive right now doesn't answer that question for me. And since it
doesn't answer that question for me, I have to be concerned that
this might be that hour. That's שמא ימות. shema yamut. Exactly. Because
there is no חזקה chazakah, on the future.
Right. Exactly. Okay. All right. So, אמר ליה רבא. amar lei Rava.
So and that is a very important distinction להלכה l'halacha that we
actually apply in a number of circumstances. Okay, so אמר ליה amar
lei in הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah and other cases, that a status
quo only tells you that the present status still remains. It doesn't
tell you that you don't have to worry that something might change
in the next minute. If she eats תרומה trumah she's not punished,
right? Well, I don't know because I mean when you're not supposed
to, you might be a פושע. poshea. אמר ליה רב אדא בר
מתנא לרבא, amar lei Rav Adda bar Matna le-Rava, והנוד, vehanod, so
the way that רבא Rava said it, he made it want to
say like everybody would agree that we're concerned about the future. Everybody
says that the present we assume is the status quo, and everybody
would agree we're concerned that he'll die in the future. But one
minute, the case of the flask of wine, דשמא ימוסו, de-shema yamusu,
that's a case of maybe it will die, and according to you
that should be a case that everybody is concerned might happen. ופליגי,
u-pligi, and it's a debate. So אמר רב יהודה מדסקרתא, amar Rav
Yehuda mi-Diskerata, שאני נוד דאפשר דמסרי ליה
לשומר. shani nod de-efshar de-masrei lei l'shomer. No, no, no. The reason
there is a debate and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir isn't concerned at
all it'll break is because as opposed to whether you'll live or
die, you know, there you can be super careful. Like it would
be possible to watch a barrel carefully that it'll never break. I
mean that's also another thing to say. Everybody's going to die, not
every barrel is going to break, okay? And you can be very
careful about watching it. So מתיב ליה רב משרשיא, masiv lei Rav
Mesharshiya, שומר צריך שומר? shomer tzarich shomer? But your שומר shomer needs
a שומר? shomer? Who's going to say that he's going to do
a good job? Okay, so although again, to me it seems like
a reasonable answer, not every barrel is going to break. Anyway, אלא
אמר רבא, ella amar Rava, שמא מת לא חיישינן, shema met lo
hashinan,
whether somebody is dead, everybody agrees we do not, we're not concerned.
That's our משנה. Mishna. The status quo still obtains. If he was
alive, we presume to still be alive. שמא ימות, shema yamut, are
we concerned that some tragedy will occur and the guy will die
in an hour from now, or the barrel will break before שבת
Shabbos comes out? תנאי, Tanna'ei, that's a debate of תנאים. Tanna'im. Okay,
so that's anyway, so the, everybody agrees to the חזקה chazakah that
a person is still alive. Are we concerned something bad is going
to happen in the next few minutes or in the next day,
right, if right now everything is okay? That's a debate of תנאים,
Tanna'im, and that might also be somewhat circumstantial, like, you know, like
the likelihood that a barrel will break, you know, what's the likelihood
a guy will die, and you know how much do, are we
concerned about those things? Who knows? Maybe the debate of תנאים Tanna'im
maybe depends case by case. Let's take a look, yeah one minute,
let's take a look at a short תוספות Tosafos which gets to
the issue that Mike was raising, which is very interesting. תוספות Tosafos
says, on the previous עמוד on כ"ז עמוד א', kaf-zayin amud aleph,
he says like this. הא רבי מאיר דלא חייש למיתה. ha Rabbi
Meir de-lo haish le-misa. So תוספות Tosafos has, השתא דמדמי שמא מת
לשמא ימות, hashta de-midami shema met le-shema yamut,
even according to who was it, אביי Abaye I think, who said
that שמא מת shema met and שמא ימות shema yamut are the
same, with you know, לא לגמרי
מדמי, lo legamrei midami, it's not a complete comparison. דרבי מאיר דמוקי
מתניתין כוותיה ולא חייש לשמא מת, de-Rabbi Meir de-muki masnisin kevasei ve-lo
haish le-shema met, אפילו זמן מרובה, afilu zman meruba, חייש לשמא ימות
לזמן מרובה. haish le-shema yamut le-zman meruba. Okay,
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right, who's the case by the barrel and
he's not concerned that the barrel will break, but we do see
in another place he's concerned that after a long period of time,
if someone, you know, somebody will die ten years from now, okay?
Not that somebody is dead, but somebody will die ten years from
now. Okay, and then he gives the whole case of יבום which
you don't have to worry about. Okay, but the point is, that
even if somebody says, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I'm not concerned
the barrel will break before שבת... Shabbos... is out, does that mean
that he would allow you to do something and not have to
worry that something might go wrong like the barrel might break in
ten years, that somebody might die in ten years? That might change
things, okay? And then תוספות Tosafos says also, okay, ורבי יהודה u'Rebbi
Yehuda goes two lines from the bottom, נמי דחייש לשמא ימות לאלתר,
nami d'chaish l'shema yamus l'altar, and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who is
afraid that the guy would die like before שבת, Shabbos, the barrel
would break before שבת Shabbos is out, okay, לא חייש לשמא מת
לאלתר, lo chaish l'shema meis l'altar, he's not going to be afraid
that somebody is dead immediately. Okay, what does that mean? דאם כן
אשת כהן שיצא בעלה מפתח ביתו, d'im kein eishes Kohen sheyatza ba'alah
mipetach beiso, when the husband goes to שול, shul, she has to
stop eating תרומה trumah because maybe he dropped dead the minute he
goes out to שול. shul. לא תאכל בתרומה, lo tochal b'terumah, ולא
תאכל כי אם בשעה שרואה בעלה בפניה, v'lo tochal ki im b'sha'ah
she'ro'eh ba'alah b'faneha, she should have to be always seeing him to
be eating תרומה. trumah. Okay, so meaning that even somebody who's concern,
you know, even even according to the opinion in the גמרא Gemara
that doesn't see a difference between שמא מת shema meis and שמא
ימות, shema yamus, תוספות Tosafos says everybody agrees there's got to be
like a difference. Okay, nobody is concerned that, you know, after five
minutes, he was healthy five minutes ago that he's dead now. Okay,
you might be concerned he'll die in the next five minutes, that's
the גמרא Gemara by the גט, get, right? Not eating תרומה trumah,
because maybe he'll die in the next five minutes, maybe the thing
will break in an hour, but nobody is afraid that if the
husband leaves the house for an hour that she can't eat תרומה
trumah. because you have to be afraid he's dead now. Okay, so
everybody agrees there's more to be concerned about about whether he will
die, you know, whether than whether he is
dead, okay. אלא שמא שמדמה לא מדמה
אלא שמא מת לזמן מרובה לשמא ימות לאלתר, ella shema shemedameh lo
medameh ella shema meis l'zman merubeh l'shema yamus l'altar, right, so right
we don't know exactly what those times are, but the point is
the גמרא Gemara it's a very these are very important distinctions in
הלכה. Halacha. Number one, that we're not concerned of שמא מת, shema
meis, and according to our משנה, Mishna our תוספות Tosafos point that
nobody could be concerned of שמא מת לזמן מועט, shema meis l'zman
mu'at, because then the woman would have to stop eating תרומה trumah.
when her husband went to שול shul or whatever, okay, went to
work. Okay, but we're not even concerned with לשמא מת לזמן מרובה.
l'shema meis l'zman merubeh. The husband goes למדינת הים, she can eat
תרומה trumah. for the next ten years. Now how long, fifty years?
I don't know. Okay, but anyway, but we're we're not concerned that's
the status quo, the status quo obtains. The question of לשמא ימות,
l'shema yamus, so it seems like the גמרא's Gemara saying that we're
not you know that's a debate, are we concerned of שמא ימות?
shema yamus? And there there actually is an important distinction between שמא
ימות לזמן מועט shema yamus l'zman mu'at and שמא ימות לזמן מרובה,
shema yamus l'zman merubeh, that we might not be concerned that somebody
will die in a short period of time but we might be
concerned that they'll die obviously in a long period of time. So
if רבא Rava is giving the answer right now about שמא מת
shema meis or שמא ימות, shema yamus, then רבא's Rava answer, is
that in all contradicting or is he חוזר chozer on his first
answer about דחוי הגבורות? dichuy hagevuros? Has nothing to do with it?
Oh no, not necessarily. He might say that those situations you don't
start with a חזקה, chazaka. you know, those create ליתא ספיקות, leisa
sfeikos, right, so that might be those might be different. But does
the גמרא Gemara effectively move away from רבא's Rava answer? It sort
of what it sort of
raised a קשיא, kashya, gave an answer, moved, yeah, it's not clear
what the גמרא Gemara does with רבא's Rava distinction. And he knows
his חזקה chazaka. supposed that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would allow the
woman to eat תרומה trumah. if she received that גט that was
effectively... yeah, because רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir not concerned about שמא ימות,
shema yamus, right, right. Okay, and then the question of the קשיא
kashya of רב משרשיא, Rav Mesharshiya, does that mean that he's a
פושע? poshea? What? But רב משרשיא, Rav Mesharshiya, ערבך ערבא צריך. arvach
arva tzarich. Not פושע, poshea, just how do you how you know,
רש"י? Rashi? רש"י? Rashi? But whatever, it means you can't trust you
know how do you know that you can trust the שומר? shomer?
Maybe the שומר shomer needs a שומר. shomer. Yeah, that לשון lashon
means your שומר shomer needs a שומר. shomer. How what you can't
say well I'll give it to somebody to trust him. ערבך ערבא
צריך, arvach arva tzarich, I got here. Okay. השולח חטאתו ממדינת הים,
so the גמרא Gemara says והא בעינן סמיכה. v'ha beinan smicha. Now
one minute, how can you send the חטאת from מדינת הים? medinas
hayam It's okay that you can assume he's alive, but the owners
have to do סמיכה smicha on the קרבן. korban Now there's a
long תוספות Tosafos that says one minute, I thought that if you're
like טמא tamei you could have a קרבן korban brought for you
even though you're not doing סמיכה. smicha. So תוספות Tosafos says, so
he works tries to work out all the cases, but the basic
answer is is that when it's possible for you to do סמיכה,
smicha, we should insist on it. Okay, if it's not possible like
you're טמא, tamei, now you could say מדינת הים is not possible,
I understand. Anyway, but that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Actually you could
even say the opposite, when it's not possible, it's כל הראוי לבילה
אין בילה מעכבת בו. kol harauy l'bilah ein bilah me'akeves bo. If
it's possible maybe it's better, if it's not possible maybe then it's
really a problem. But anyway, it is true that the גמרא Gemara
allows a טמא tamei person to have a קרבן korban brought for
him, but that's because it's there's no choice. But here at least
the גמרא Gemara says why do we allow this without any hesitation?
Isn't there shouldn't the owners have to be present to do סמיכה?
smicha? So the גמרא Gemara says והא בעינן סמיכה, v'ha beinan smicha,
אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, בקרבן נשים, b'korban nashim, it's a
קרבן korban of women and women do not have to do סמיכה
smicha on their קרבנות. korbanos. רב פפה אמר, Rav Pappa amar, בחטאת
העוף, b'chatas ha'of, it's a bird sacrifice and you don't do סמיכה
smicha on bird... according to both of them, if it wasn't, then...
it's sounding like that according to them you would not accept a
קרבן korban, from מדינת הים for a normal man's animal sacrifice. You
would tell him come and do it yourself. Now again, this תוספות
Tosafos works that through because it's not true, there are cases where
we allow the person not to be present. So but at least
as a לכתחילה lechatchila we would not allow it. Okay. וצריכא V'tzricha
you need all three cases. דאי אשמעינן גט משום דלא אפשר. De'i
ashmi'inan get mishum d'lo efshar. If it said גט that's because you
know there's no alternatives, the woman's got to get on with her
life. So you have to rely on the חזקה. chazaka. אבל תרומה
דאפשר Aval trumah de'efshar but תרומה Terumah where maybe she could just
eat חולין, chulin, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe I would say don't
rely on the חזקה. ואי אשמעינן תרומה דזימנין דלא אפשר, Ve'i ashmi'inan
trumah de'zimnin d'lo efshar, if it was תרומה there's times where she
doesn't have a lot of money and she can only really afford
תרומה. So therefore you can rely on the חזקה. אבל חטאת העוף
מספק לא ליכול לזר, Aval chatas ha'of mi'safek lo leichul l'zar, but
a חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, you know, it's okay, don't bring the
קרבן, wait until he next comes to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
צריכא, Tzricha, so it's telling you even though there's no urgency, we
go ahead and we let it being brought. Okay, תוספות Tosfos deals
with the whole question that actually חטאת העוף chatas ha'of is brought
on a ספק, safek, but anyway moving on. Okay, שלושה דברים אמר
רבי אלעזר בן פרטא לפני חכמים וקיימו את דבריו. Shlosha devarim amar
Rabi Elazar ben Parta lifnei chachamim ve'kiyemu es devarav. Three things Rabbi
Elazar ben Parta said to the sages and they affirmed his position.
על עיר שהקיפוה כרכום, Al ir she'hekifuha karkom, on a city surrounded
by a siege, that's some word that means a siege, an Aramaic
word, ועל הספינה המטרפת בים ve'al hasfina hamitorefes bayam and a ship
that's being caught in a storm, ועל היוצא לידון ve'al hayotzei lidon
and somebody who is being brought to a court to be judged
on a capital crime, שהן בחזקת קיימין. shehein bechezkat kayamin. So since
we dealt with can you assume the old guy is still alive
when you deliver the גט, how about these people and you want
to deliver a גט to their wife, or they assigned a גט,
or their wives are כהנים Kohanim and their wives want to eat
תרומה, and what you know is last heard the ship was caught
in a storm at sea. Last heard he was being brought up
on a capital, you know, there was a, he was being tried
on capital charges. In which court? Okay well the גמרא Gemara will
get to it. So can you assume that he is still alive?
Or the city was besieged? In all those cases, in all those
cases you can assume that they're still alive. אבל עיר שכבשה כרכום,
Aval ir she'kvasha karkom, but when it's been, but once it's been
conquered by the siege, once it's been actually overtaken, וספינה שאבדה בים
ve'sfina she'avda bayam and the sea is lost, lost at sea, ship
is lost, lost at sea, excuse me, not sea, ship is lost,
lost at sea, okay, and והיוצא להרג ve'hayotzei l'hareig and actually after
the judgment has been passed and the person is now going to
be, he's on death row, and it's not like the United States
where it's twenty years, okay, he's on what do you call it,
he's waiting to be hanged, the judgment has been passed, נותנין עליהם
חומרי חיים וחומרי מתים. nosnin aleihem chumrei chayim ve'chumrei meisim. Now those
people you don't know for sure that they're alive, but you also
can't assume they're dead. Okay, so what would be that case? So
בת ישראל לכהן, bas Yisrael l'Kohen, if it's a בת ישראל bas
Yisrael married to a כהן, Kohen or בת כהן לישראל, bas Kohen
l'Yisrael, לא תאכל בתרומה, lo tochal b'trumah, you can't eat תרומה. Meaning
if it's a בת ישראל Yisrael married to a כהן, Kohen she
has to assume he might be dead and then she's no longer
part of the כהן family and can't eat תרומה. But if it's
a בת כהן bas Kohen married to ישראל, if he's dead then
she goes back to being part of her father's כהן family and
she can eat תרומה. She has to assume he might still be
alive and therefore she cannot eat תרומה. Is there a time limit?
I don't know, I don't
know. Okay, so אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, I mean you
do have that whole פרק perek in יבמות Yevamos about people reporting
on death and עד אחד eid echad and so on. Okay, so
maybe, you know, and that would sort of seem, that's not a
time limit, but that allows certain, you know, certain low threshold of
evidence to allow her to assume that he's dead. But until then
she has to be מחמיר machmir both ways. Is that the biggest
חומרא? chumra? Yeah, there's no seven year rule or something. Okay, the
biggest חומרא chumra is that she can't remarry obviously. אמר רב יוסף
לא שנו אלא בבית דין של ישראל. Amar Rav Yosef lo shanu
ela b'Beis Din shel Yisrael. When is this that we assume that
being brought up for judgment, I'm
sorry, that after judgment has been passed, you're not yet definitely considered
to, the guy's not definitely considered to have been executed? That's only
a בית דין Beis Din of ישראל that might be even after
judgment has been passed might be prepared to retract it. אבל בבית
דין של עובדי כוכבים כיון דגמירי לדינא לקטלא מנקיט קטלי, Aval b'Beis
Din shel ovdei kochavim keivan d'gamiri l'dina l'katla minkat katlei,
once the judgment has been passed they're not going to retract it.
Now presumably this means after a certain period of time has passed,
like it's not instantaneous, I don't know, like two minutes after the
judgment has been passed. But whatever, but after whatever period of time
has been passed you're not חושש choshesh for any retractions. Okay, so
אמר ליה אביי בית דין של עובדי כוכבים נמי מקבלי שוחדא. Amar
lei Abaye Beis Din shel ovdei kochavim nami mekablei shochada. What do
you mean? Even the non-Jewish court, you know, you pay off the
right people, so it's possible, so it's not definite. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, he said back no, כי שקלי מיתמי דליחתום פורסישנמאג, ki shakli
mi'temi d'lichtom pursishnamag,
I don't know what that is, when do they, when are they
willing to take bribes before the actual final sealing of judgment has
been written. Okay, or תוספות Tosfos says maybe it's the name of
a particular ruler and before he affixed his signature to it. לבתר
דמחתים פורסישנמאג לא שקלי, Lebasar d'machtim pursishnamag lo shakli, after this guy
or this act has been done, then it's too late. Okay. To
take bribes, okay, nobody it'll be too obvious. Okay. So after a
certain point, it ain't being retracted. מיתיבי, Meisivi, ask on this, כל
מקום שיעמדו שנים ויאמרו עדים אנו את איש פלוני kol makom sheyaamdu
shnayim veyomru eydim anu es ish ploni שנגמר דינו בבית דין של
פלוני shenigmar dino beveit din shel ploni ופלוני ופלוני עדיו, uploni uploni
adav, הרי זה ייהרג. harei ze yeihareg. Somebody
escapes from the from the prison and then witnesses appear in and
where in the city that he escaped to and they say, we
testify that we were in such and such a city and we
were in the בית דין Beis Din and we heard his judgment
passed and these were the witnesses and this was the בית דין
Beis Din and it was judged that he was a, you know,
he was passed to be executed. So that's testimony is accepted and
they'll execute him in the other city. Okay, so in that case,
הרי זה ייהרג. harei ze yeihareg. So anyway, what's the story? The
story is you're telling me that even after the judgment has been
passed in a בית דין של ישראל, Beis Din shel Yisrael, retraction
is possible and with something to be concerned about in terms of
whatever, you know, this guy's status. So why do we operate on
this testimony? Why don't we say who knows, maybe even after that
happened, other evidence came to light and maybe they retracted it? So
the גמרא Gemara gives the obvious answer. The גמרא Gemara says, דילמא
בורח שאני. dilma boreiach shani. No, that the guy of an escapee,
you know, you don't have the full luxury of worrying in that
case about maybe other evidence came to light. You have to deal
with the evidence at hand and in the vast majority of cases
it will end, you know, they don't retract it. So there, you
don't worry about that possibility of retraction. Okay, but it still is
possible and in our case when it comes to eating תרומה or
other things we have to be חושש choshesh maybe it was retracted
even after גמר דין. gmar din. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. שמע מבית דין של ישראל Shama
mibeis din shel Yisrael שהיו אומרים shehayu omrim איש פלוני מת, ish
ploni meis, איש פלוני נהרג, ish ploni neherag, ישיאו את אשתו. yasiu
es ishto. They heard that from the in a from a Jewish
court, an announcement was made that a certain person was executed or
a certain person died while he was being held as prisoner, okay,
ישיאו את אשתו, yasiu es ishto, they can assume he's died and
allow his wife to remarry. He's dead. If you heard so מפי
קומנטריסין, mipi kumantrisin,
whatever that means, the courts של עובדי כוכבים shel ovdei kochavim איש
פלוני מת, ish ploni meis, איש פלוני נהרג, ish ploni neherag, אל
ישיאו את אשתו. al yasiu es ishto. You cannot assume that that's
true. Now why not? That says he's actually dead. מאי מת ומאי
נהרג? mai meis umai neherag? What does it mean dead and what
does it mean that he was killed? Okay. אילימא מת מת ממש
ונהרג נהרג ממש? elima meis meis mamash v'neherag neherag mamash? You
literally mean that they're announcing that he actually has been executed or
died while he was held prisoner? דכוותיה
גבי עובדי כוכבים d'kavasei gabei ovdei kochavim אמאי אל ישיאו את אשתו?
amai al yasiu es ishto? Why not marry off his
wife? הא קיימא לן, ha kayma lan, we have a
principle, דכל מסיח לפי תומו d'chol masiach lefi tumo הימנוה רבנן. heimnuha
rabanan. They believe them in terms to remarry the
wife. That's that whole פרק perek in יבמות Yevamos and that's even
of a non-Jew.
So why shouldn't you believe the court that they're saying the guy
is dead? אלא לאו, ela lav, it must mean when it's talking
about that they're announcing he's dead, מת meis means יוצא למות. yotzei
lamus. It doesn't mean that they're actually announcing that he's dead. It
means that he's in the process of dying or he's going he's
being brought out to die, okay, maybe he's going to be left
bound up in the desert and left to die. נהרג neherag יוצא
להריגה. yotzei l'hareigah. ונהרג u'neherag means he's going to be brought out
to be executed. So they're announcing what they're about to do to
him, not what happened already. וקתני בבית דין של ישראל ישיאו את
אשתו. vkasni beveit din shel Yisrael yasiu es ishto. And it
sounds, this sounds too to be the exact opposite of what רב
יוסף Rav Yosef is saying. That in a בית דין של ישראל
Beis Din shel Yisrael you can assume that they're not going to
retract, but in the בית דין Beis Din of non-Jews, that's when
you have to assume that who knows, maybe they'll be bribed and
maybe they'll retract. It's the exact opposite. There's more of
a concern that it'll be reversed in the בית דין Beis Din
of non-Jews, the exact opposite of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So the
גמרא Gemara, says, one
minute it says like this, ולעולם מת ממש ונהרג ממש. u'l'olam meis
mamash v'neherag mamash. No,
it's talking that they really are announcing that he's dead or that
he's
executed. ודקאמרת, v'dka'amart, and if that's true, why not trust the non-Jewish
court? דכוותיה גבי עובדי כוכבים אמאי לא? d'kavasei gabei ovdei kochavim amai
lo? Why not trust the non-Jewish court? הא קיימא לן דכל מסיח
לפי תומו הימנוה רבנן. ha kayma lan d'chol masiach lefi tumo heimnuha
rabanan. We believe people when they're just talking in their innocence. הני
מילי במילתא דלא שייכא בה. hani mili bemilsa d'lo shaycha bah.
That's if it's something that they're that they don't have a vested
interest, if they're not it's not they're not the actual principal party.
אבל במילתא דשייכא בה, aval bemilsa d'shaycha bah,
here these are the prison is announcing, right? The court system is
announcing. So now you could say it's the opposite. If they're announcing
they take particular responsibility not to be misrepresenting. אבל עבדי לאחזוקי שיקראו.
aval avdi l'achzukei shikrahu. But the גמרא Gemara's is saying the opposite.
You don't know what people's vested interest is. Maybe they want people
to believe that look, you know, we said we were going to
execute him and we executed him, and they people make up stories
sometimes, okay? So if they've got a vested interest, they're not an
disinterested party, you can't necessarily believe. Okay, that's an important question, how
much does that true for the הלכה halachah of יבום and for
I mean for those הלכות halachos of trusting somebody to remarry the
wife. I mean, the irony is that you know what, is that
if a witness testifies that the woman is dead, he can wind
up marrying the woman. So, I mean, there are cases like that
in the גמרא, Gemara you
know. This means if you like modern day so if you read
like something in the paper you can't you know like about the
death announcement you can't you know if you're No the paper is
a disinterested party. They're not the people that are in charge of
actually getting the guy killed. Okay? Okay. איכא דאמרי אמר רב יוסף
Ikka d'amri Amar Rav Yosef anyway according to that we kept although
the evidence was against it we that was רב יוסף's Rav Yosef's
position that we're more concerned that the only case we're concerned that
it didn't happen was a בית דין של ישראל. beis din shel
Yisroel. But a בית דין beis din of the non-Jews they'll definitely
going to see it through. Now the גמרא's going to do the
exact opposite. Okay and go through the exact same proofs and it'll
work out better. איכא דאמרי אמר רב יוסף Ikka d'amri Amar Rav
Yosef some say רב יוסף Rav Yosef says לא שנו בית דין
של עובדי כוכבים. lo shanu beis din shel ovdei kochavim. When are
we not certain whether it actually happened? That's in a non-Jewish court.
אבל בית דין של ישראל Aval beis din shel Yisroel in a
Jewish court כיון דנפיק לדינא לקטלא קטלי ליה keivan denafik l'dina l'katla
katli lei once they have decided they're going to execute they'll execute.
Now he doesn't deny the fact that there is a הלכה halacha
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin which is that they could retract. It is true,
even if the guy's about to be put up on the gallows
a company says and finds new evidence you review the case. But
nevertheless he says that's extreme, extremely rare and therefore by a בית
דין של ישראל beis din shel Yisroel we'll assume he's dead okay
against the משנה. When does the משנה say he might still be
alive? When he was going to be executed by a non-Jewish court.
Why is it more likely there that they'll retract? So אמר ליה
אביי בית דין של ישראל נמי אפשר דחזו ליה זכותא? Amar lei
Abaye beis din shel Yisroel nami efshar d'chazu lei zchusa? So we
don't assume he's dead right? Right. So why is it? Right. I
mean it's possible that they'll retract. Right. אמר ליה אביי בית דין
של ישראל נמי אפשר דחזו ליה זכותא Amar lei Abaye beis din
shel Yisroel nami efshar d'chazu lei zchusa one minute, by a Jewish
court why do we definitely assume isn't
it possible that they'll reopen the case? No. כי חזו זכותא מקמי
דמיגמר דינא. Ki chazu zchusa mikamei d'migmar dina. When are they really
prepared to look at other evidence or when does that happen more
commonly? Before גמר דין gmar din before the case has been sealed.
Right. Sentencing has been sealed. בתר דמיגמר דינא תו לא חזו ליה
זכותא Basar d'migmar dina tu lo chazu lei zchusa after the sentencing.
Now it doesn't mean that they never do again the הלכה halacha
is is that they are prepared to do it, but it just
means in practice it really never happens. So okay or it's highly
unlikely. But the non-Jewish court
didn't say it but the real reason is is because a non-Jewish
court the assumption is could be bribed and therefore it's more therefore
there is more of a concern that they didn't actually carry it
out. Okay. לימא מסייע ליה Leima mesayei lei let's try to support
you. כל מקום שיעמדו שנים ויאמרו מעידים אנו את איש פלוני שנגמר
דינו בבית דין של פלוני ופלוני ופלוני עדיו הרי זה יהרג. Kol
makom sheya'amdu shnayim veyomru me'idim anu es ish ploni shengmar dino b'beis
din shel ploni u'ploni u'ploni adav harei zeh yeihareig. They testify that
somebody was sentenced in another court you accept the testimony and you
execute the guy and you see you're not concerned that it might
be overturned. So you see we're not concerned about being overturned in
a Jewish court. So it says no דלמא בורח שאני dilma boreiach
shani that's where we don't really have any choices so we're not
concerned. That doesn't mean we that doesn't prove we would never be
concerned that it had been overturned. תא שמע Ta shma come in
here. שמע מבית דין של ישראל שהיו אומרים איש פלוני מת איש
פלוני נהרג תשיא את אשתו Shama m'beis din shel Yisroel shehayu omrim
ish ploni mais ish ploni neherag tasi es ishto when it's announced
by a Jewish court that somebody died was executed you can marry
his wife. מבית דין של עובדי כוכבים איש פלוני מת איש פלוני
נהרג אל תשיא את אשתו M'beis din shel ovdei kochavim ish ploni
mais ish ploni neherag al tasi es ishto from a non-Jewish court
that somebody had been executed you cannot. So מאי מת ומאי נהרג
Mai mais u'mai neherag what does this mean? אילימא מת ממש נהרג
ממש Ilima mais mamash neherag mamash so if it means literally died
and executed? דכוותיה גבי עובדי כוכבים dichvosei gabi ovdei kochavim so when
the non-Jewish court announces it אמאי אל תשיא את אשתו amai al
tasi es ishto why not marry the wife? הא קיימא לן כל
מסיח לפי תומו הימנו הימניה ha kaima lan kol mesiach l'fi tumo
heiminu haymneih that the rabbis believe even in those cases to remarry
the wife? אלא לאו Ela lav מת mais must mean יוצא למות
yotzei lamus that they're announcing that he is is that he's going
out to left to die. And נהרג neherag יוצא להרג yotzei leihareig
he's going to be executed. וקתני בבית דין של ישראל תשיא את
אשתו V'kasni b'beis din shel Yisroel tasi es ishto you can assume
it will happen when you're dealing in a Jewish court. But בבית
דין של but b'beis din shel but in a non-Jewish court it
might not. So that's exactly supports רב יוסף Rav Yosef this version
of רב יוסף Rav Yosef that there is more likelihood in a
non-Jewish court that it won't I mean it'll be definite in a
Jewish court and in a non-Jewish court that's when you have a
doubt whether it actually happens. So the גמרא says no לעולם מת
ממש ונהרג ממש le'olam mais mamash v'neherag mamash no it means that
they are saying he died and was killed. דכוותיה גבי עובדי כוכבים
Dichvosei gabi ovdei kochavim and similarly by the non-Jewish court so then
why can't you marry his wife? אמאי לא והא קיימא לן דכל
מסיח לפי תומו הימנו הימניה Amai lo v'ha kaima lan d'kol mesiach
l'fi tumo heiminu haymneih so don't we say that you can trust
even in those cases? No. הני מילי במילתא דלא שייכי בה אבל
במילתא דשייכי בה עבידי לאחזוקי שיקרא. Hani mili b'milsa d'lo shaichi bah
aval b'milsa d'shaichi bah avidi l'achzukei shikra. The exact same סוגיא sugya
except here it's come here it's he had the flip position. Okay
so all the evidence supports the position that by the non-Jewish court
that by a Jewish court we can actually assume that they did
it. By a non-Jewish court that's where we have an element of
doubt. Okay. And that was seemed to be this last case about
when the court announced it. But in the end we said that
no, that case might be that they're actually just announcing that
he actually is dead. And even so maybe we don't believe the
non-Jewish court in this case because they're a vested party. Okay. They
have a vested interest for for for lying. That's the שייך shaich
but what's what's he died, we executed him. Right. They said they
were going to execute him and they and then people are saying
no but they say we executed him. We didn't actually do anything
with them, but they want to save face. Something, yeah. When people
have vested interests they make up stories for you know there's a
million reasons. Okay, even if from the non-Jewish court.